Guide to the General Young Marshall Moody family papers, 1852-1955 MS 404
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
General Young Marshall Moody family papers
1852-1955
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Moody, Young Marshall, 1822-1866
MS 404
0.5 Linear Feet 1 box
The bulk of the correspondence is from Young M. Moody to his "Dear and Confiding Wife.", written during the U.S. Civil War. In addition there are other family letters, military correspondence, land and business records, photographs, daguerreotypes and badges of rank and an epaulet from General Moody's uniform.
(1 box)
Biographical Note
Young M. Moody (1822-1866) was an Alabama businessman before the start of the U.S. Civil War. He joined the army and eventually went with the Alabama 43rd Regiment, which came under the command of Brigadier General Archibald Gracie (1832-1864). The Alabama 43rd was in some of the worst fighting of the war. Colonel Moody was wounded sometime in 1863. When General Gracie was killed on December 3, 1864, Colonel Moody took over command of the Brigade and was promoted to Brigadier General in March 1865. At the war's end General Moody and his family moved to New Orleans where he died of a fever in the fall of 1866.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the correspondence is from Young M. Moody to his "Dear and Confiding Wife.", written during the U.S. Civil War. In addition there are other family letters, military correspondence, land and business records, photographs, daguerreotypes and badges of rank and an epaulet from General Moody's uniform.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Alan Buster, 1986
General note
Portions of this collection are available online at https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/62316.
Index Terms
Subjects
American Civil War (United States: 1861-1865); Soldiers; Social life and customs
Document Types
corrrespondence; bills of sale; photographs; daguerreotypes
Subjects (Persons)
Moody, Young Marshall, 1822-1866; Gracie, Archibald, 1832-1864
- Series I: Bills, Deeds, Statements, Promissory Notes, 1852-1893, 187506 (Folder 1)
  - Bills, Deeds, Statements, Promissory Notes, 1852-1893, 187507
- Series II:Correspondence and personal ephemera, 1860-1955, 187459 (Folder 2)
  - Y.M. Moody to "Dear Annette," Cairo, Illinois, November 22, 1860, 187505
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Memphis, Tenn. December 2, 1860, 187504
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Mobile, April 26 1862, 187503
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Chattanooga, Tenn. July 5, 1862, 187502
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Knoxville, Tenn. January 4, 1863, 187501
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Knoxville, Tenn. February 10, 1863, 187500
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Knoxville, Tenn. February 20, 1863, 187499
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Knoxville, Tenn. February 23, 1863, 187498
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, (location unknown), March 8, 1863, 187497
  - Y.M. Moody to son, Cumberland Gap, Tenn. June 4, 1863, 187496
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Cumberland, Tenn. June 12, 1863, 187495
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Knoxville, Tenn. July 8, 1863, 187494
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Brig Hd Qtrs, Morristown, Tenn. December 24, 1863, 187493
  - John T. Wade to Mrs. Moody, Demopolis, Ala, July 12, 1864, 187492
  - Y.M. Moody to wife. Near Manchester, Va., July 26,1864, 187491
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Near Manchester, Va., August 9, 1864, 187490
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, In the Trenches before Petersburg, Va. December 26, 1864, 187489
  - Y.M. Moody to son, In Trenches Petersburg, Va., January 4, 1864 (sic), 187488
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Mobile, Ala., June 17, 1865, 187487
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Mobile, Ala., July 13, 1865, 187486
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Mobile, Ala., July 24, 1865, 187485
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Mobile, Ala., August 26, 1865, 187484
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, Mobile, Ala., September 30,1865, 187483
  - Y.M. Moody to son, Mobile, Ala., May 25, 1866, 187482
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, New Orleans, June 20, 1866, 187481
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, New Orleans, July 3, 1866, 187480
  - Y.M. Moody to son, New Orleans, July 20,1866, 187479
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, New Orleans, August 7, 1866, 187478
  - Y.M. Moody to son, New Orleans, August 20, 1866, 187477
  - Y.M. Moody to wife, New Orleans, September 12, 1866., 187476
  - W. Langford (?) to Mrs. Moody, Mobile, October 8, 1870, 187475
  - A.E. Moody to sister, Linden, May 24, 1872, 187474
  - Mrs. Waring Mikell to Mrs. Moody Charleston, SC., July 10 1874, 187473
  - Charles C. Jones, Jr., to Mrs. Moody, New York City September 17, 1873, 187472
  - Charles C. Jones, Jr., to Mrs. Moody, New York City, November 3, 1875, 187471
  - Bessie D. and Frank O. Norris to Mrs. Moody Alleyton, TX June 10, 1876, 187470
  - L.W. Toulmin to Mrs. Moody, Toulminville, February 19, 1879, 187469
  - Ann T. Hunter to "Dear Sister Moody," Mobile, Ala., March 19, 1883, 187468
  - Ann T. Hunter to Mrs. Moody, Mobile, March 26, 1883, 187467
  - C.L. Moody (son) to Gen. J.B. Gordon, Lampasas, Texas, March 24, 1892, 187466
  - Cornelia Adams (Moody) to Annette (Moody), Manchester, Va., August 29, 1892, 187465
  - Cornelia Adams (Moody) to Annette Moody, Manchester, Va., May 27, 1896, 187464
  - Universal Protective Association to "Dear Sir and Brother," Los Angeles, California, January 5, 1897, 187463
  - Mrs. Walter Bass to Mrs. Moody, Mobile, Ala., April 17, 1901, 187462
  - Page 5 of letter from "your devoted aunt, Cornelia" (probably Cornelia Adams Moody), undated, 187461
  - Photo copies of additional correspondence to and from Y.M. Moody, 187460
- Series III: Y.M. Moody personal documents and ephemera, 187457
  - Y.M. Moody personal documents and ephemera (Tax List 1859, including numbers of enslaved persons, amount of income; petit point example; telegrams; a poem entitled "Mother's Love", 187458 (Folder 3)
- Series III: Photographs, 1866-1907 and undated, 187446 (Folder 4)
  - James Moody and Gen. Young M. Moody (8x10, b/w copy print) (cousins), 187456
  - James Moody and Gen. Young M. Moody (4"x6.5", original studio print from Photograph Gallery, 920 Main St., Richmond, VA) (cousins), 187455
  - Miss Willie Moody, June 22, 1866 studio portrait (2.5"x4"), 187454
  - James Moody and Young M. Moody? As young men? Studio portrait, (2.5"x4"), 187453
  - Unidentified boy, studio portrait, tintype, mounted in 3"x5" card, 187452
  - Snapshot of Moody family outside home at 2307 Preston Ave., Houston, TX, circa 1907:Mrs. General Y.M. Moody, granddaughter Virginia Anne Moody (Clarkson), grandson C.L. Moody, Jr., 187451
  - Unidentified studio portrait of man seated at table, slightly defaced by inkmarks emphasizing eyes and hair., 187450
  - James Moody and Gen. Young M. Moody, hand colored daguerreotype cased in dark wood, same image as above, 187449
  - General Archibald Gracie, 43rd Regiment, beloved friend of Gen. Y. M. Moody. Cased in brown wood, hinge broken., 187448
  - Unidentified young woman in gown. Cased in leather with gold leaf and mother of pearl, case broken., 187447
- Series IV: Military related papers and uniform items, 1861-1863, 187444 (Folder 5)
  - Glove (probably military), uniform buttons, collar devices showing rank, shoulder epaulet., 187445 (Folder 6)
- Series V: Bills of Sale, 1859-1860, 187441 (Folder 7)
  - "Jane", enslaved female, 16 years of age, 1860, 187443
  - "Smith", enslaved male, 40 years of age, Linden, Alabama, April 1859, 187442